Guide to the Mito Kruth Papers ALBA.240
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mito Kruth Papers
1912-1986
1926-1950
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Kruth, Mito, 1899-
ALBA.240
0.75 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Mito Kruth was a Finnish-American who fought as a volunteer in the Spanish Civil War, first in the Washington Battalion and later in the Abraham, Lincoln Brigade. This collection contains letters he wrote during his time in Spain, as well as correspondence from the mid-1930s when he worked in Michigan as an organizer for the Communist Party. Kruth's letters reflect his dedication to the Communist Party, as well as his identity as a Finnish-American. Mito and his wife Helen (later Helen Leiviska) traveled extensively, both in Europe and in the United States, and their correspondence documents their travels. The collection also includes Mito Kruth's passport, his father's naturalization papers from 1912, and various documents from Finnish-American organizations. Throughout many periods of his life, Mito went by the first name Neils.
Provenance
The Mito Kruth collection was donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Madeline Baron of Minneapolis, Minnesota, in early 2006, and then transferred to the Tamiment Library, NYU.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Mito Kruth was born December 24, 1899 in Finland to Mathilda and Frank Kruth. When Mito was 12, his family moved from Finland to the United States and settled in Brooklyn. Much of the correspondence in this collection consists of letters exchanged between the Mito Kruth and his wife, Helen, who were often separated by their travels. The date of their marriage is uncertain, but by 1937-38 she was using the name Helen Kruth.
Mito worked as an organizer for the Communist Party in Ironwood, Michigan and Superior, Wisconsin in the mid-1930s. He set sail for Europe in March of 1937 to volunteer in the Spanish Civil War. He first served in the Washington Battalion and later in the Abraham Lincoln Battalion. During his time in Spain, he suffered a gun-shot wound to the leg and was hospitalized for several months.
Upon his return from Spain, he continued to do Communist Party work in the Upper Peninsula of Michigan and in Wisconsin. Mito and Helen traveled extensively overseas. In the late 1940s, Mito bought land in Trumansburg, New York and worked as a farmer. His letters illustrate his commitment to the Communist Party as well as his strong ties to Finnish-American communities in the Midwest and in New York.
The date of Mito Kruth's death is not known, but in the mid- or late 1970s Helen married George Leiviska, another veteran of the Lincoln Brigade. The couple resided for some years in Minneapolis. George Leiviska died in 1982.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Correspondence contains letters written by Mito to Helen over the course of 38 years, including the period of his service in the Spanish Civil War. With the exception of his letters from Spain, all of his letters are signed "Neils" and that seems to have been his preferred name while living in America. His other correspondence details his experience organizing for the Communist Party in Wisconsin, Michigan, Upstate New York and Washington, DC. There is correspondence from Helen to Mito written during a trip she took to Europe in 1948. Also included in this collection are letters to Helen written by a variety of correspondents.
Series II: Subject Files contains Frank Kruth's naturalization papers, Mito's passport, the mortgage and deeds to his land in Trumansburg, New York, and various documents from Finnish-American organizations. There is also a sampling of maps and postcards from the Kruths' travels abroad.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into two series:
Missing Title
I, Correspondence, 1926–1982.
II, Subject Files, 1912–1986.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Separated Material
Photographs from the Kruth Papers have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library in ALBA Photo #36.
Superior (Wis.).; Ironwood (Mich.); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Hospitals.; Barcelona (Spain); Articles.; Personal papers.; Correspondence.; Finnish American newspapers.; Madrid (Spain); Finnish Americans.; Leiviska, Helen Kruth, 1907-1989; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Kruth, Mito, 1899-
- Series I: Correspondence,1926-1982
  - Arvola, Ranse Edward to Helen Kruth, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Kruth, Helen to George Leiviska (Second Husband), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Kruth, Helen to Mito Kruth, Mar 1948-Apr 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Kruth, Helen to Mito Kruth, May 1948-Jun 1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Kruth, Helen to Mito Kruth, Jul 1948-Aug 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Kruth, Helen to Mito Kruth, Sep 1948-Dec 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Kruth, Mito to Helen, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Kruth, Mito to Helen, Apr 1905 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Kruth, Mito to Helen, Apr 1937-May 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Kruth, Mito to Helen, Jun 1937-Jul 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Kruth, Mito to Helen, Aug 1937-Sep 1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Kruth, Mito to Helen, Oct 1937-Dec 1937 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Kruth, Mito to Helen, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Kruth, Mito to Helen, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Kruth, Mito to Helen, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Kruth, Mito to Helen, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Kruth, Mito to Helen, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Kruth, Mito to Helen, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Kruth, Mito to Helen, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Kruth, Mito to Helen, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Maki, Martin D. to Helen, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Various Correspondents to Helen Kruth Leiviska and Mito Kruth, undated, 1938-1982 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Postcards, undated, 1946-1986 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1912-1986
  - Certificate of Naturalization - Frank Valentin Kruth, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Farm Policy at the Democratic Advance Platform Committee Hearing, May 6, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Finnish-American Mutual Aid Society, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Finnish Relief Fund, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Finnish Writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - National Committee of Finnish-American Trade Unionists, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Passport, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Personal Documents, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Toveritar: Organ of the Finnish Working Women in America, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Travels: Maps, Postcards, etc., undated (Box 2, Folder 10)